Guide to the Barbara Evans Papers 1974-2007
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Barbara Evans papers
1974-2007
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 900
Evans, Barbara, b. 1934
4.0 linear feet
This collection documents Barbara Evans’ twenty-eight year political career as a county commissioner in Missoula County, Montana. Materials date from 1974, four years before her first election, to 2007, the year Evans retired from political office. The collection provides a look into Evans’ career as a Republican commissioner in a traditionally blue county, and more generally, provides perspective on the experience of women in local government.
Biographical Note
Barbara Evans was born in Cheyenne, Wyoming, in 1934. She moved with her family to Missoula, Montana, in 1940. She served as Missoula City Police Commissioner and served as a County Commissioner in Missoula County, Montana, for twenty-eight years. She began her political career in 1978, at the age of forty-four, as a member of the Republican Party. Some of her noted accomplishments as County Commissioner include her efforts to expand Reserve Street, support for the removal of the Milltown Dam, and work on numerous other land and infrastructural developments. In terms of political achievements, Evans is remembered as the first women elected to the Missoula County Commission and, in 1986, she was part of the first all-female county commission in the United States. Evans retired in 2007.
This collection contains information on Barbara Evans’ twenty-eight year political career as a Missoula County Commissioner in Missoula, Montana. The collection contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, campaign and election materials, photographs, awards, press releases, scrapbooks, and posters that convey political happenings both directly and indirectly related to Evans’ political career. The bulk of the material is newspaper clippings. The collection highlights some of Evans political achievements including her work on the Reserve Street expansion, her efforts to remove the Milltown Dam, involvement in numerous housing, industrial, and infrastructure developments, as well as some of her political controversies that included her clash with democratic commissioners Bob Palmer and Germaine Conrad.
this collection was organized in two series.
Series I: Unbound Materials, 1976-2007, 0.8 linear feet.
Series II: Scrapbooks, 1974-2007, 3.4 linear feet.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
the chain of custody of this collection is currently unknown.
this collection was donated to the University of Montana archives by the Missoula Public Library in 2017.
Junk mail and materials unrelated to Evans or Missoula County were removed from the collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Women--Political activity--Montana--Missoula; Political participation--Montana--Missoula; Elections--Montana--Missoula; Women legislators--Montana--Missoula
Politics and Politicians; Missoula; Montana
- Unbound Materials, 1976-2007; Series I; 0.8 linear feet
  This series consists of newspaper clippings, correspondence, campaign and election materials, photographs, awards, press releases, and posters.
  Upon acquisition, the unbound materials lacked any semblance of organization and as a result have been arranged by material type.
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Clippings, circa 1976-2007 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - General correspondence, circa 1981-2007 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Campaign materials from Evans and other candidates, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Campaign Finance Materials, 1976, 1990, 1997 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Election materials, 1978, 1990, 1997 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Reserve Street landscaping plan, 1995 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Montana Disincorporation Info Sheet, undated (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Handbook for Montana women running for public office, 1976 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - FERC [Federal Energy Regulatory Commission] materials, 2000 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Posters, 1980, 1985, 1996 and undated (Box OS 16)
- Scrapbooks, 1974-2007; Series II; 3.2 linear feet
  This series consists of scrapbooked news clippings, correspondence, campaign and election materials, photographs, press releases, speeches, and awards related to Evans career and Missoula County politics during her time as a county commissioner. The scrapbooks contain both integrated and loose materials. All scrapbooks contain undated material.
  Within the scrapbooks, loose materials have been left in the location they were found.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1974-1975 (Box OS 3)
  - Scrapbook 2, 1975-1977 (Box OS 3)
  - Scrapbook 3, 1976 (Box OS 3)
  - Scrapbook 4, 1976 (Box OS 4)
  - Scrapbook 5, 1978-1978 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook 6, 1976-1980 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 7, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook 8, 1978 (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook 9, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbook 10, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook 11, 1980-1988 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook 12, 1981-1996 (Box OS 12)
  - Scrapbook 13, 1997 (Box OS 13)
  - Scrapbook 14, 1995-1996 (Box OS 13)
  - Scrapbook 15, 1996 (Box OS 13)
  - Scrapbook 16, 1996 (Box OS 14)
  - Scrapbook 17, 2001, 2007 (Box OS 14)
  - Scrapbook 18, 1984-2002 (Box OS 15)
  - Scrapbook 19, 1984-2007 (Box OS 15)